Finding Aid for Harley Harris Bartlett Papers 1909-1960
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Harley Harris Bartlett Papers
1909-1960
Bartlett, Harley Harris, 1886-1960.
Professor of botany and director of the Botanical Gardens at the University of Michigan. Correspondence, research notes, forty-nine volumes of diaries, and other papers relating to his professional career, including his botanical expeditions to South America and the Philippines and his interest in the Phoenix Project of the University of Michigan; also a history of the botany department of the University containing material on Mark W. Harrington, professor of astronomy and director of the University Observatory; and photographs.
Aa/2; 85701
11 linear feet
13 film reels in 4
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection came to the library in 1961 from the Bartlett estate (donor no. 2008 ).
The collection is open to research. Original film restricted, DVD use copy available and streaming file available on request.
The 16mm films in the collection were digitized in 2009 as part of a library video preservation project. Preservation master beta tapes for all titles and high resolution digital files of some titles were created along with DVD and streaming files for all titles. The DVDs are available for use in the library. A selection of the streaming files may be available online at a given time, others can be mounted on request.
Harley Harris Bartlett was born March 9, 1886 in Anaconda, Montana, and attended high school there and in Indianapolis. He graduated from Harvard in 1908 receiving his BA in chemistry. For the following six years he was associated with the Bureau of Plant Industry of the U.S. Department of Agriculture as a chemical biologist.
He came to the University of Michigan in 1915 as acting assistant professor of botany Six years later he came professor, and from 1922 to 1947, he served as chairman of the department of botany. From 1922 to 1955 Bartlett was director of the Botanical Gardens. He retired from the University in July 1956.
During his years at the University, Bartlett had a particular interest in the botany of tropical countries and he conducted botanical explorations in Formosa, Sumatra, Mexico, British Honduras, Guatemala, the Philippines, Panama and South America. Much of his work in Central and South America was concerned with the research for sources of rubber there. From 1940 to 1944, he served as the principal botanist in government-sponsored rubber investigations in the Philippines, Haiti, Argentina, Uruguay, Chile and Mexico.
Bartlett died February 21, 1960.
The collection has been divided into the following series: Correspondence; Phoenix Project of the University of Michigan; Miscellaneous; Diaries; and Other Bound Records.
A significant portion of the collection is the diaries that Bartlett maintained from 1926 to 1960. Included are detailed diary entries for the period 1934-1935 when he was an exchange professor of botany at the University of the Philippines. While in the Philippines, Bartlett also compiled Philippine English vocabularies and a two-volume Sambali-English-Tagalog vocabulary.
Subjects:
Bartlett, Harley Harris, 1886-1960.; Botany.; Harrington, Mark Walrod, 1848-1926.; Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; South America.; United States. Office of Rubber Investigations.; University of Michigan. Matthaei Botanical Gardens.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Botany.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Bartlett, Harley Harris, 1886-1960.; Botany.; Hatcher, Harlan, 1898-1998.; Offices.; Philippines--History--1946-1986.; Picnics.; University of Michigan. Matthaei Botanical Gardens.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, undated; 1909-1960
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1909 (Box 1)
  - 1911-1934, 27 folders (Box 1)
  - 1935-April 1940, 23 folders (Box 2)
  - May 1940-August 1943, 20 folders (Box 3)
  - September 1943-April 1953, 25 folders (Box 4)
  - May 1953-1960, 19 folders (Box 5)
- Phoenix Project of the University of Michigan, 1952-1954
  - Notebook, November 1952 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, April 1953 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, November 1953 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, April 1954 (Box 6)
  - Papers, 1952 (Box 6)
  - Papers, 1953-1954 (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous
  - Newspaper clippings, 1922-1954 (Box 6)
  - Philately
    - Correspondence, 1947-1960 (Box 6)
    - Articles, undated (Box 6)
    - Papers, 1947-1955 (Box 6)
  - Miscellanea concerning Harley H. Bartlett, 1908-1953 (Box 6)
  - Papers concerning miscellaneous scientists, 1931-1942 (Box 6)
  - Papers concerning the Botany department and the University of Michigan, 1921-1955 (Box 6)
  - Papers concerning work for the Office of Rubber Investigations, 1940-1943 (Box 6)
  - Papers concerning botany and botanical organizations, 1909-1958; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Photographs (Box 6)
    Portraits; photographs of Bartlett doing botanical research in Haiti; photographs of Bartlett with friends in the Philippines, and at the Botanical Gardens; and contact sheet photographs of Bartlett in his study.
  - Essays concerning botanical subjects, 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Papers concerning work in the Philippine Islands, 1935-1949; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Notebook containing references for bibliographical supplement to "Fire in Relation to Primitive Agriculture and Grazing in the Tropics" (Box 7)
  - Papers concerning Asa Gray Bulletin, 1952-1956 (Box 7)
  - Miscellanea, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Papers concerning linguistics (summation), 1938-1950 (Box 7)
  - Reprints (Box 7)
  - Appointment book, 1922 (Box 8)
- Diaries, 1926-1959
  - Diary, 1926 (Box 8)
  - Diary of trip to Far East, 1926-1927 (Box 8)
  - Diary, 1927-1935; 9 volumes (Box 8)
  - Philippine diary, September 1935 (Box 8)
  - Philippine diary, November 1935 (Box 8)
  - Philippine diary, 1935 (Box 8)
  - Diary, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Diary, 1938-1941; 5 volumes (Box 9)
  - Diary, 1942; 2 volumes (Box 9)
  - Diary, 1943; 2 volumes (Box 9)
  - Diary, 1944 (Box 9)
  - Diary, 1945 (Box 9)
  - Diary, 1946 (Box 9)
  - Diary, 1947 (Box 10)
  - Diary, 1948 (Box 10)
  - Diary, 1949 (Box 10)
  - Diary, 1950 (Box 10)
  - Diary, 1951 (Box 10)
  - Diary, 1952 (Box 10)
  - Diary, 1953 (Box 10)
  - Diary, 1954 (Box 10)
  - Diary of Washington-Florida trip, 1954 (Box 10)
  - Diary, 1955 (Box 10)
  - Diary, 1956 (Box 10)
  - Diary, 1957 (Box 10)
  - Diary, 1958 (Box 11)
  - Diary, 1959 (Box 11)
- Other bound materials
  - Harvard University student notebooks
    - Record of Ash and Soil Analysis (Box 11)
    - Mathematics V (Box 11)
    - Chemistry (Box 11)
  - Sambali-English-Tagalog vocabulary, 2 volumes (Box 11)
  - Philippine-English vocabularies, 4 volumes (Box 11)
  - History of the Botany Department of the University of Michigan, circa 1951 (Box 11)
  - Journal (in form of extended letter) concerning life and experiences in Sumatra, 1918; photocopy (Box 11)
- Motions Pictures
  The films consist of 13 original films compiled into four reels. The films are in part ethnographic in nature, showing a variety indigenous ceremonies and village activities and some shots Bartlett family members and friends.
  - Philippines Film No. 1, undated; 85701-1
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:15:55 @ 18 fps
      [Restricted]
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 1)
    - Streaming File: 85701-1, flash flv
  - Philippines Film No. 2, undated; 85701-2
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:14:22 @ 18 fps
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 1)
    - Streaming File: 85701-2, flash flv
  - Philippines Film No. 3, undated; 85701-3
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:10:28 @ 18 fps
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 1)
    - Streaming File: 85701-3, flash flv
  - Philippines Film No. 5, undated; 85701-5
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, ca. 00:22:00 @ 18 fps